<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sad nevvs from the seas being a true relation of the losse of that good ship called the Merchant Royall which was cast away ten leagues from the lands end on Thursday night being the 23 of Septemb. last, 1641</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17137</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12863291</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12863291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59233)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 255:E172, no 21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sad nevvs from the seas being a true relation of the losse of that good ship called the Merchant Royall which was cast away ten leagues from the lands end on Thursday night being the 23 of Septemb. last, 1641</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Woodcut of sailing vessel on t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Merchant Royal (Ship)</term>
               <term>Marine accidents --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94707:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Sad Nevvs from the Seas.</p>
            <p>Being a true relation of the loſſe of that good Ship called the <hi>Merchant Royall,</hi> which was caſt away ten leagues from the Lands end, on Thurſday night, being the 23. of Septemb. laſt, 1641. having in her a world of treaſure, as this ſtory follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doth truly relate.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of ship</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94707:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94707:2"/>
            <head>Sad newes from the Seas.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Sayling is an art that is not to be undervalued by any, is confeſt; that Kingdomes and Countries are inri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thereby; that what other lands yeeld, this hath i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by this art as well as they; that by this art gold and ſilver is conveyed unto us from the Indies, fine Silks and Sattins from another climate, ſpices and fragrant ſmels from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other climate, and this by interchange, which this art benefits both Kingdomes, Nations, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and this by that famous admired art of Sailing, and brought to paſſe, now let us leave this art ſo worthy of prayſe, and looke a while on an object of ſorrow, and waile our brothers loſſes as our owne.</p>
            <p>The Royall Merchant (or Merchant Royall) ſome foure yeares ſince ſailed out of this land as a ſhip hired here for the King of Spains imployment in the Weſt India, ſhe ſayled out in company with other ſhips, but when come into Cales the Captain was by ſome oppoſition like to be put by, and was a while diſmiſſed, ſo that giving over his hopes of the Weſt India imployment, received fraught, and from Cales ſayled into the Mediterranean unto the Iſland of Majorcke, one of the King of Spaines Iſlands: in the meane, or about the time, S. Galleons
<pb facs="tcp:94707:3"/>being bound for the Weſt India, one of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſmall fire was whole burned downe with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and looſed from her cables, did her ſelfe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge all her braſſe Ordnance, and burned 3. dayes and 3. nights under Pountal, moſt part of the goods were aſhore, not yet loaden aboord; in place of which Galleon this Royall Merchant was thought (as being a ſhip they might command, and of great burthen) to bee a fit veſſell to take aboord the firſt Galleons goods or loading; a Mandate from the King of Spaine commanded this Royall Merchant from her Majorck voyage to make ſayle for Cales with all expedition, and to ſtand in place of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Galleon, tooke aboord her goods, and ſayled with the other 7. Galleons in company into the Weſt or Spaniſh Indies: the Kings commands o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd, they proceed, and this Engliſh ſhip caried moſt of the beſt Spaniſh governours, commanders, and gentry, whereby it redounded great benefit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very meaneſt of the Engliſh, both in ſayling thither, traffiquing there, and fraughted richly home with great numbers of rich paſſengers, which with rich fraught made the Engliſh a great voyage. Some dangers they paſt, but ſafely arived in Cales, where they continued afore they could prepare themſelves for England at leaſt 7. or 8. months, at end of which they diſimbogu'd for England in company of Captaine <hi>Legend</hi> of Dover, in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Merchant, a luſty ſtout ſhip of 400. tunnes, and 28. caſt peeces of Ordnance; they ſayled together, the Royall Merchant in ſtreſſe of foule weather
<pb facs="tcp:94707:3"/>ſprung a leake in the bottome of the ſhip, to that the ſaylers were forced to tend the pumpe day and night: Captaine <hi>Legend</hi> not liking Captaine <hi>Lim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryes</hi> courſe, with joynt conſent ſhaped another courſe ſome pount in variation, ſo that they did not abſolutely part ſuddenly, but glide ſidingly from each other night came on, and foule weather, they plyed their two chaine pumps, in midſt of which labour both the pumpe chaines broke at once, and fell into the Wells, ſo that before they could any way recover and mend the chaines, they bad got 4. foot water in the hold. They labour at their pumps with great ſtrength, but could not prevaile over what was got in, but did keepe her in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, nor more nor leſſe diminiſhing.</p>
            <p>They being ouerlaboured could hardly pumpe more to any purpoſe; ſome of the Sea-men to the number of 30. got into the long boat, cut her off, and called to the Captaine to ſave himſelfe, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it, and would have a Merchant, his paſſenger, to ſave himſelfe, he anſwered hee had lived long in Spaine, and with great trouble got up 10000. pound, and now would ſtay by it, for his life hee valued not, the Captaine anſwered him it was all one whether he went in the boate or no, for they were in no better eſtate then thoſe left aboord, having in the boat no oares, maſts, ſailes, or any thing to keepe the boate afar the Sea, and muſt needs periſh undoubtedly: being thus in deſpaire they eſpied a light at which they ſhot off 30. piece of ordnance, it prooved to bee Captaine <hi>Legend</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:94707:4"/>who on conſideration of the Royall Merchants diſtreſſe returned to helpe them; they obſerving their danger and the ſhip ſinking, ſent forth then long boate, which at divers times ſaved the men, but durſt not come neare the ſhip, ſo that the men to ſave their lives were faine to ſling themſelves in tackles, and ſo ſwing from the ſinking ſhip into the boate, who caught hold of their cloathes with their boate hooks; the Captaine was the laſt, who would not forſake her untill ſhee was ſunke even unto her Cook-roome ports, and then got into the boate: 7. men that went downe on the lower deck, (or orlope) to breake up a cheſt of gold, never came up the ſhip ſuncke ſo faſt on them. This ſhip was 700. tuns, 36. caſt peeces of ordnance, 80. ſeamen, beſides paſſengers, ſhe had in her 300000. pound in ready boloigne, 100000. pound in gold, and as much value in Iewels, beſides each mans adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the whole Cargaſon, or rich lading of the ſhip, all which was ſunke in the ſea, nothing ſaved. The Captaine on his landing repaired to his houſe and family, with a hankercher about his neck, and will not be ſeene or ſpoken with (as yet) by any his griefe is ſo great: his name is Captaine <hi>Iohn Limbry</hi> living neere Ratcliffe Croſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
